there are so many great piano tutorials
on YouTube but most of them assume you
already have certain Knowledge and
Skills this quick start video will get
you up to speed even if you never seen a
piano by the end of this video you'll be
playing some impressive sounding music
and be ready to go forth and learn your
favorite songs and you'll avoid common
bad technique habits that are hard to
fix and hold so many aspiring players
back most people have this idea that
learning piano takes years of brutal
practicing it doesn't if you just want
to have fun playing your favorite
popular songs maybe impress your friends
and family or play an open mic night you
can make it happen really quickly you
don't even have to read cheet music if
you give me the next 11 minutes of your
time I will get you well on your way so
grab the cheat sheet using the link
below that's got a visual Guide to
Everything in this lesson subscribe to
my channel and let's jump
in okay so this is a piano keyboard it
might look overwhelming but first thing
to notice is there's this pattern of the
black Keys they're found in groups of
two and groups of three this is just the
top of a group of three that was cut off
then two 3 2 3 2 3 I'm moving from low
to high right now so these are the
highest notes on the keyboard these are
the lowest notes we use this pattern as
a map to know which note in the musical
alphabet we're playing sing the musical
alphabet song A B C D E F G that's it
there are only seven notes in the
musical alphabet first note we'll find
is C middle C specifically and you'll
find that right at the bottom of the
group of two black keys that is most
centered it might sound weird to talk
about C before a but middle C ends up
being a really important note and a lot
of things in piano get referenced in
relation to it any note on the keyboard
that looks like this sitting at the
bottom of a group of Two Black Keys is
also a c so these are all C's you can
tell they kind of sound the same but
it's just higher and lower versions of
the note C and the distance between two
of the same note like this is called an
octave so here's the cool part between
middle C and this next C and octave up
is every single note there is to know on
the piano we've got the seven white keys
that make up the musical alphabet and
the five Black Keys which I'll get to in
a minute but that's all the notes you
ever need to know because all 88 keys of
the keyboard is just higher and lower
versions of those same notes so let's
look at these white keys if you count
backwards from that middle C C B a a b c
d e f g a b c d e f g a it just repeats
there is no h I have a few tips for
remembering these notes of course at
first you might just be counting in
either direction from C need to play a g
you can think C D E F G but you'll want
to get it more automatic we can quickly
add another anchor note the note that's
at the bottom of the group of three
Black Keys is f f f it can help to
visualize and say the notes that are
surrounding each of the groups of Black
Keys around groups of two we've got c d
e c d e c d e d is in the middle and D
is for dog it kind of looks like a
little dog with black ears around groups
of three we have f g a and b f g a b f g
a b but at the end of the day the best
way to get them ingrained is just
through repetition I recommend quizzing
yourself find a
b find an e and you can check your work
using the cheat sheet you'll get faster
and faster until it becomes fully
automatic so what about those Black Keys
first in music a half step is the
distance between one note and the very
next note this distance is the same as
moving by a fret on the guitar to Sharp
a note means to move it a half step
higher and the sharp symbol looks like a
number sign or a hashtag so if this is C
this is C Sharp if this is f here's F
sharp to Flat a note means to move it
down a half step and the flat symbol is
this weird little lowercase b so here's
an a here's an A flat here's an e e flat
so every black key has two names you can
call this an fshp you can also call it a
g flat so I haven't been using very good
technique so far to play these notes you
can only get so far with using one
finger so let's look at our hands in
piano we use all 10 of our fingers and
we can refer to each by a number and we
do all the time it's super important to
burn these numbers into your mind thumbs
are one pinkies are five 1 2 3 4 five
here's right hand fourth finger left
hand third finger it seems really easy
but be careful because if you get really
used to playing with your right hand
where the lowest note is one and the
highest note is five it's really easy to
accidentally call this one I can't tell
you how common that mixup is so just
remember it's a mirror and notice how
I'm curving my fingers because if I
straighten them they're all different
lengths and that's not very conducive to
the straight line of the keys so we
curve our fingers like we're holding a
softball bringing them all into line and
playing on our fingertips and while
we're at it you want your bench to be at
a height where your belly button is
about even with the keys elbows at a
right angle or a little bit more so you
don't want to be a T-Rex and you don't
want to be a zombie sitting up as
straight as you can but nice and relaxed
everything kind of just hangs and lets
go except for your wrists float up you
can imagine a little string tied around
your wrist letting them float up so you
can play on your fingertips but your
shoulders should stay relaxed so let's
start playing some notes you'll probably
notice it first your fingers feel a
little bit clumsy so let's do a simple
finger exercise find middle C with the
first finger on your right hand and
we're going to play 1 2 3 4 5 4 3 2 2 1
that's c d e f g f e d c if you find
yourself hitting multiple notes at the
same time you're not alone you're using
your muscles in a new way so just take
it really slow it takes a minute for
them to wake up by doing this exercise
your fingers will figure it out just
keep reminding yourself to use that good
technique wrist up playing on the
fingertips everything else is right
relaxed when you get the hang of this do
the same thing in your left hand one
octave lower take it as slow as you need
the finger numbers are the opposite
remember 5 4 3 2 1 2 3 4 5 practice your
hand separately at first but then when
you get the hang of it you can try them
together and over time you can get it
faster once you get the hang of that try
moving your left hand down two steps to
start on a
you get this really nice
Harmony sounds super
cool okay now that your fingers are
starting to figure out how to play I
want to teach you a few Chords chords
are when you have a few notes played
together and the backbone of most music
especially popular songs and rock music
it's all based on chords first let's try
an A minor chord you're going to do it
like this that's a c and e using right
hand Fingers 1 3 and five you might find
your second and fourth fingers trying to
get involved that's really common just
be patient with those fingers they will
figure it out especially with that
finger exercise so that's an A minor
chord minor chords have that sad sound
which I love and if it was Major it
would sound like this so you can hear
the difference there major sounds happy
minor sounds
sad a lot of music is made from chord
progressions a sequence of chords so
let's take a few more chords and put
them in order if you can play that a
minor chord you can play these other
chords cuz they're all the exact same
shape the next chord IS F major so we're
going to find this F down here with our
thumb same shape f a c that's a major
chord sounds kind of happy if it was
minor it would sound like that but it's
not next we're just coming up to C major
same shape you can just kind of move
your hand up here till the thumb is on
that middle C so that's also a major
chord c e and G and then finally we're
going to do a G major chord so you're
going to come to down here thumb on G G
B and D okay so if we put those chords
all together in order as a chord
progression we could write it out like
this the little lines are dividing the
measures which each get the same amount
of counts in this case and you'll find
as most commonly the case we're in 44
time which is a fancy way of saying that
each of those measures gets four counts
1 2 3 4 1 2 3 4 you want to keep a
steady count whenever you play 1 2 3 4
so we hit this little symbol with the
two dots that's a repeat sign it means
you start over again 3 4 1 2 3 4 let's
give the left hand a job to do the left
hand is going to be our bass player and
we're just going to do a single note on
the note that the chord is named after
so for the a minor we're going to play
an
A for the F we're going to play an F for
the c major we're going to play
C for the G major we're going to play G
I'm using third fifth 1st and fourth
fingers so we can just keep that hand in
the same position the whole time take
your time with this but then put them
together one 2 3 4 1 2 3 4 sounds like a
song you could uh write your own vocals
to
this today I'm going to learn piano
yeah and you can add cool rhythms to it
1 2 3 4 just playing the right hand on
every count you could even do it twice
as fast 1 and 2 and three and four and 1
and 2 and 3 and four and 1 2 and 3 and
four and one final thing to try is
called an arpeggio and that's when you
break the notes of a chord apart and
play a pattern with them arpeggios are a
great way to instantly make beautiful
music Here's here's the pattern and I'll
just demonstrate on the a minor at first
left 1 3 5 and you can just repeat
that so it's just one count for each
note going up bottom middle middle top
and I'm kind of just holding the left
hand down but we could do the chord
progression maybe do two times through
that pattern for each and it would sound
like
this
sounds really
cool so just take your time with this
and have fun maybe you change the
octave now that you know how to play
these four chords I want to show you
just five of the thousands of songs you
can now play so check check out this
video next and have
fun